This is Beaverton, Oregon. It's within
这里是俄勒冈州比弗顿市。 自 20 世纪 70 年代以来，耐克公司总部就设在
this wooded, comparatively quiet
这个绿树成荫、相对安静的
Portland suburb where Nike's been
波特兰郊区
headquartered since the '70s. It's here
。
on this 400-acre campus replete with a
在这个占地 400 英亩的校园里，有
jogging trail, a running track, a soccer
慢跑道、跑道、
pitch, a basketball gym, a research lab,
足球场、篮球馆、研究实验室
and countless office [music] buildings
和无数的办公（音乐）大楼，
where Nike is desperately trying to get
耐克正竭尽全力让
their business back on track. Peaceful
自己的业务重回正轨。
on the outside, panic has mounted within
表面上风平浪静，但随着该公司
the company as it loses market share in
在其开创的运动鞋市场中市场份额不断下降，公司内部恐慌情绪日益加剧
pioneer. Bungling launches and failing
。 由于产品发布失败和
to innovate, America's largest shoe
创新乏力，美国最大的鞋业
company is in a funk.
公司陷入了低谷。
While 67% of the company's total revenue
虽然公司总收入的 67%
comes from shoes, nowhere on this campus
来自鞋类，但在这个园区里
will you actually find a shoe factory.
你却找不到任何一家鞋厂。
fact, will you find a Nike-owned shoe
事实上，在美国乃至全世界，你都找不到耐克自己拥有的
factory because Nike's not a shoe maker.
鞋厂，因为耐克本身并不是鞋类制造商。
[music] Its business is more abstract.
[音乐] 它的业务更加抽象。
The company's SEC filings will tell you
该公司向美国证券交易委员会提交的文件会告诉你，
it's not a shoe company at all, but
它根本不是一家鞋业公司，而是将
rather list the Nike and Swoosh design
耐克和 Swoosh 设计
trademarks as its most valuable [music]
商标列为其最有价值的[音乐]
assets. To Phil Knight, the company's
资产。 对于公司创始人菲尔·奈特（
founder now in his late '80s, Nike's
现年已近九十岁）来说，耐克的
business is inspiring and innovating for
业务是激励和创新
athletes, while the filings call it a
运动员，而提交的文件则称其为一家
company that provides design,
提供
selling of athletic footwear, apparel,
运动鞋、服装、
equipment, [music] accessory, and
设备、[音乐]配件和
services. In other words, Nike's not a
服务的设计、开发、全球营销和销售的公司。 换句话说，耐克不是一家
shoe maker, but a tastemaker. And
鞋类制造商，而是一家潮流引领者。 而
tastemaking, when it comes to shoes, is
说到鞋子，品味这东西就像
a pretty [music] fickle business.
音乐一样变化无常。
Shoes are tools, but not just for
鞋子是工具，但不仅仅是用来
walking and working. A study by
走路和工作的。
researchers at the University of Kansas
堪萨斯大学的研究人员进行的一项研究
has shown that when subjects are just
表明，当受试者仅
shown someone's footwear without any
看到某人的鞋子而没有任何
other context, they're able to guess
其他背景信息时，他们能够
with fairly high accuracy the age,
相当准确地猜测出该人的年龄、
gender, income range, and even
性别、收入范围，甚至
personality traits and political
性格特征和政治
leanings of the person in question. The
倾向。 这项
finding only backs what consumers
发现只是印证了消费者
already knew, though. People judge based
早已知晓的事实。 人们会
on shoes and recognize they get judged
根据鞋子来评判他人，并且意识到自己也会
based on shoes, so they make shoe
因为鞋子而被评判，所以他们会
choices to cultivate an image or tell
选择鞋子来塑造形象或讲述
their own personal story, whether that
自己的个人故事，无论
be who they are or [music] who they
是他们是谁，还是他们
aspire to be. Extroverts will reach for
渴望成为谁。 外向的人会选择
norm-disrupting red shoes, while those
打破常规的红色鞋子，而那些
hoping to not stick out will prioritize
不想引人注目的人则会优先选择
quieter shoes and bland styles, for
更安静的鞋子和更平淡的款式，例如
[music] instance. One way or another, we
（音乐）风格。 无论从哪个角度来看，我们都
use shoes to understand others, and so
通过鞋子来了解他人，因此，
we in turn select shoes to help frame
我们反过来也会选择鞋子来帮助塑造
how people think of ourselves. Shoe and
别人对我们的看法。 鞋子和
shoe selection tell stories, and Nike
鞋子的选择本身就蕴含着故事，而耐克
used to be the best storyteller.
曾经是最会讲故事的品牌。
If you don't know the story of Nike's
如果你不了解耐克的
rise, it's laid out across the map of
崛起故事，那么
the company's campus. At the end of 1
公司园区的地图上就详细地展示了它的发展历程。 位于
Bowerman Drive, named after the company
以公司联合创始人命名的鲍尔曼大道 1 号尽头，
co-founder, on the shore of Lake Nike,
毗邻耐克湖畔，与
neighboring the Michael Jordan and John
迈克尔·乔丹和约翰·麦肯罗
McEnroe buildings, and across from the
大楼相邻，与
Ronaldo field, is Steve Prefontaine
罗纳尔多球场隔街相望，坐落着史蒂夫·普雷方丹
Hall, appropriately at the core of the
大厅，它恰如其分地位于
campus. Few characters embody the Nike
校园的中心位置。 很少有人能
story like Steve Prefontaine, or Pre,
像史蒂夫·普雷方丹（简称普雷）那样体现耐克的故事，
and that's by design. Before Nike was a
而这正是耐克的用意所在。 在耐克成为
giant, before it was even called Nike,
巨头之前，甚至在它被命名为耐克之前，
it was little more than the young
它只不过是年轻
ambitious Phil Knight, a lifetime runner
有为的菲尔·奈特（Phil Knight）——他本人是一位终身跑步爱好者——
himself, importing [music] sleek
进口时尚的
Japanese running shoes. It was a
日本跑鞋而已。 它曾是一个
disruptor, a plucky underdog, a fighter
颠覆者，一个勇敢的弱者，一个在 20 世纪 70 年代初
market share in a nascent American
美国新兴慢跑热潮中试图抢占一小块市场份额的斗士
1970s. At about the same time that Nike
。 就在耐克
started getting momentum, a scrappy
开始获得发展势头的同时，一位来自俄勒冈州
runner from an old coastal logging town
一个古老沿海伐木小镇的顽强跑者也
in Oregon was beginning to rise.
开始崭露头角。
Prefontaine ran distance events for the
普雷方丹在
University of Oregon under coach Bill
俄勒冈大学教练比尔·
Bowerman, who was also designing running
鲍尔曼的指导下参加长跑项目，鲍尔曼当时还在
shoes for Nike. As Pre began to
为耐克设计跑鞋。 随着普雷逐渐
establish himself as America's best
确立自己作为美国最佳
distance runner, it was only natural
长跑运动员的地位，
that he join the brand. But Pre is
他加入该品牌也就顺理成章了。 但普雷
central to Nike's rise, not just because
对于耐克的崛起至关重要，不仅因为
he was a good at track, but because of
他擅长田径，更因为
how he went about being good at track.
他擅长田径的方式。
Prefontaine won a host of collegiate
普雷方丹赢得了众多大学
titles, he set American records, he went
冠军头衔，创造了美国纪录，并
to Munich in 1972 to represent the US at
于 1972 年前往慕尼黑代表美国参加
the Olympics. He was an undeniable
奥运会。 他是一位毋庸置疑的
talent. He was also a character. He was
天才。 他也是个很有个性的人。 他出身于
a working-class kid from a tough
一个艰苦的
industrial town. He was small, scrappy,
工业小镇，是工人阶级的孩子。 他个子矮小，性格坚韧，
handsome, and brash. He was cocky, but
相貌英俊，但为人鲁莽。 他虽然自负，但
he backed it up with a work ethic that's
他的职业道德至今仍受到
still revered in American running
美国跑步
culture. He appeared on the cover of
文化的推崇。 他
Sports Illustrated at 19. His races were
19岁时就登上了《体育画报》的封面。他的比赛
aired on national TV. His go Pre
在国家电视台播出。 他的“支持Pre”
t-shirts became so popular they were met
T恤衫大受欢迎，结果却遭到了“
by a backlash of stop Pre shirts. He was
停止Pre”T恤衫的强烈抵制。 他是
an American star, [music]
一位美国明星，[音乐]，
and he wore Nike.
而且他穿耐克鞋。
When signed to the company, Pre repped
签约公司后，Pre
Nike shoes at run clubs and public
在跑步俱乐部和公众聚会上穿着耐克鞋
meetups. He traveled to high school and
。 他前往高中和
college programs to demo them. He sent
大学进行演示。 他把这些照片寄给了
world. He pushed the product, and the
世界各地的朋友和竞争对手。 他力推这款产品，而这位
producer, [music] a brash upstart of its
制作人，[音乐]本身就是一个桀骜不驯的新兴力量
own, embodied the kid's spirit.
，体现了年轻人的精神。
Nike was doing it their own way, too,
耐克也在以自己的方式做事，推出
with shoes that pushed the boundaries,
突破界限的鞋子，
first with the Nike Cortez that added
首先是耐克Cortez，它
midsole cushioning for runners. They
为跑步者增加了中底缓震。
then took the technology another step
然后，他们又将这项技术
forward with the Nike Waffle Trainer,
向前推进了一步，推出了 Nike Waffle Trainer，这款鞋
designed to be lightweight and grippy
设计轻便、抓地力强，
while staying comfortable and padded.
同时又保持了舒适性和缓冲性。
Ultimately, a fatal car crash claimed
最终，一场致命的车祸夺去了
Pre before he was able to wear his own
普雷的生命，他甚至还没来得及穿上自己的
signature shoe, the Pre Montreals, but
签名鞋款——普雷蒙特利尔鞋，但
his indomitable spirit had catalyzed
他不屈不挠的精神却催生了
[music] a movement. Title IX and
一场音乐运动。 第九条修正案和
televised track races and marathons
电视转播的田径比赛和马拉松比赛
helped spur a running boom that saw an
推动了跑步热潮，据
estimated 25 million new runners enter
估计，十年间美国新增了 2500 万跑步爱好者
the scene in the US across the decade,
，
and they wanted to be like [music] Pre.
他们希望像[音乐] Pre 一样。
They went with Nike, the upstart all
他们选择了耐克，这家新兴公司专注于
about running and innovating comfortable
跑步，不断创新舒适的
shoes that were also worn by the most
跑鞋，而
iconic and inspirational runner the US
美国音乐界最具标志性和鼓舞人心的跑步运动员也穿着耐克的鞋子
[music] had produced. The running
。 跑步
revolution transformed the American shoe
革命也改变了美国的鞋类
landscape, too. As running took off and
市场格局。 随着跑步运动的兴起和
the shoes became more comfortable, it
跑鞋变得越来越舒适，人们
became okay to wear trainers not to
不再仅仅为了
train, but in everyday life. At the
训练而穿运动鞋，而是在日常生活中穿着运动鞋也变得可以接受了。
beginning of the 1970s, athletic shoes
20 世纪 70 年代初，运动鞋
only accounted for one in every 12 pairs
仅占鞋类
sold. By 1979, it was one [music] in
销量的十二分之一。 到 1979 年，每
four pairs. The shoe game had
四对音乐中就有一对是这样的。 鞋类行业发生了
transformed, and Nike was in the middle
翻天覆地的变化，而耐克正处于这场变革的中心
of it.
。
By 1980, Nike made up 50% of all running
到 1980 年，耐克占据了
shoe sales in the US and was quickly
美国跑鞋市场 50% 的份额，并
closing the gap on Adidas in total
在运动鞋总销售额方面迅速缩小与阿迪达斯的差距
athletic shoe sales.
。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; And with the success of the Pre
随着与 Pre 合作的成功
partnership, Nike now had a model to
，耐克现在有了一个可以
grow into other spaces, too. It
扩展到其他领域的模式。 它
recognized a trend, in this case an
发现了一种趋势，即
uptick in running and jogging in the US.
美国跑步和慢跑人数的增加。
It found someone who embodied the
它找到了一位能够体现这种
movement, and then it leaned into it,
运动精神的人，然后便深入其中，
[music] creating further demand and
[音乐]进一步推动了这种运动，并创造了更大的需求和
momentum within the movement. It
动力。 它敏锐地
recognized what was becoming cool and
察觉到哪些事物正在流行，并
helped make it cool at the same time.
同时推动了这些事物的流行。
But fashion changes fast, and in the
但时尚变化很快，到了
'80s, culture went urban. Jogging shoes
80 年代，文化走向了都市化。 跑步鞋
weren't cool, basketball shoes were. It
并不酷，篮球鞋才酷。 它
caught Nike flat-footed, reporting its
让耐克措手不及，耐克
first losses in 1984 and sending it
在 1984 年首次出现亏损，并
scrambling to reinstate Phil Knight's
紧急恢复菲尔·奈特
active control of the company to fight
对公司的积极控制，以对抗不断
back on the encroaching Converse,
逼近的匡威、
&gt;&gt; [music]
新百伦和锐步。 耐克有
model, but neither the shoe nor the
模特，但既没有鞋子，也没有合适的
athlete. Then it set its crosshairs on a
运动员。 然后，它将目光投向了
young promising player in Michael
年轻有为的球员迈克尔·
Jordan.
乔丹。
While the legacy may speak for itself
虽然如今的成就无需赘言——
today, as Michael Jordan would become
迈克尔·乔丹成为了
the best basketball player in the world
世界上最好的篮球运动员，
and the Jordan brand, a branch of Nike,
而耐克旗下的乔丹品牌也
would itself become one of the largest
成为了
shoe brands in the world, the strategy
世界上最大的鞋类品牌之一——但
at the time was extremely bold. [music]
当时的战略​​却极其大胆。  [音乐]
with basketball dominance, Jordan was
乔丹并非选秀状元，而且他所打的位置当时还与篮球统治地位无关，因此，
league when he went into the National
当他进入美国国家
Basketball Association. Nike was making
篮球协会时，很难说他会成为联盟的门面人物。 耐克押注的是上涨潜力
a bet on upside. Without a past in
。 由于之前没有涉足
basketball shoes and far behind the
篮球鞋领域，而且远远落后于
Converse and Adidas basketball brands,
匡威和阿迪达斯篮球品牌，
they had to be bold to compete and
他们必须大胆竞争，并发挥
creative to find a niche to gain a
创造力找到一个利基市场，才能
foothold in the space and to convince an
在这个领域站稳脚跟，并说服
entirely unconvinced Jordan to even join
完全不相信的乔丹加入
the brand in the first place. They
该品牌。 他们将
melded bold and creative with a shoe
大胆创新与鞋履
design and marketing campaign all in
设计及营销活动融为一体
one.
。
At the time, basketball shoes to be worn
当时，NBA球员穿的篮球鞋
in the NBA had to be 51% the color
必须有51%的面积是
white.
白色。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; But Nike had an idea. Make a flashy,
但耐克有一个想法。 做一双炫酷、
colorful Michael Jordan shoe, ignore the
色彩鲜艳的迈克尔·乔丹球鞋，无视
rule, and simply deal with the
规则，然后承担
consequences. It'd be worth the
后果。
visibility regardless, it fit the brand,
无论如何，这样的曝光度都是值得的，它符合品牌形象，
and it excited the player. In 1984, a
也激发了玩家的兴趣。  1984 年，
rookie Michael Jordan took the court
新秀迈克尔·乔丹穿着
with shoes that intentionally broke the
故意违反
rules, and Nike paid the $5,000 fine. It
规则的球鞋上场比赛，耐克公司为此支付了 5000 美元的罚款。 真是
was genius. Ultimately, he'd only wear
天才之举。 最终，
them on three occasions that season as
那个赛季他只穿了三次，因为
the NBA promised to make a stronger
NBA 承诺
stand on the issue should it persist,
如果这个问题持续下去，将会采取更强硬的立场，
but three times proved plenty. They
但三次就足以说明问题了。 他们大力
pushed the Jordan I on the message that
推广 Jordan I，传达的信息是：
not only is this your new favorite
这不仅是你最喜欢的
player's shoe, it's a shoe so radical
球员鞋，而且这双鞋如此激进
and counterculture it's banned from the
和反主流，以至于被
game it's designed for. The shoe, in
它所设计的比赛所禁止。 这款鞋一经推出便
turn, sold out immediately and totaled
迅速售罄，
$126 million in sales in its first
在上市的第一年就实现了 1.26 亿美元的销售额
[music] year.
。
Nike stuck to the same playbook as they
耐克在
grew into other realms. It was
拓展其他领域时，始终坚持采用同样的策略。
Prefontaine and running in the '70s, it
70 年代是普雷方丹和跑步，
was Jordan and basketball in the '80s,
80 年代是乔丹和篮球，
it was Tiger Woods and golf in the '90s,
90 年代是泰格·伍兹和高尔夫，
Ronaldo and soccer in the 2000s. Nike
2000 年代是塞雷娜·威廉姆斯和网球，以及罗纳尔多和足球。 耐克之所以能
became the world's biggest by backing
成为世界最大的公司，是因为它支持
the mold-breakers and acting like they
那些打破常规的人，并且表现得就像他们
were the bold up-and-comers themselves.
是那些大胆的后起之秀一样。
They had an edge. They were for winners.
他们占了优势。 它们是为胜利者准备的。
[music] They didn't make excuses, they
[音乐] 他们没有找借口，他们
just did it. And customers took it hook,
只是做了。 顾客们完全信以为真
line, and sinker.
。
But a problem, and a fundamental one at
但这是一个问题，而且是一个根本性的问题
When a company is born out of the idea
当一家公司诞生之初只是一个
of a scrappy underdog disruptor, but
不屈不挠、颠覆行业的弱者，但最终却
succeeds to the point where it's now the
成功成为
industry leader, it's hard to maintain
行业领导者时，要保持
that same identity and relentless drive.
同样的个性和不懈的动力就变得非常困难。   时间
Fast forward to the 2026 Winter Olympic
快进到2026年冬季
Games. What you see is Team USA [music]
奥运会。 你看到的是美国队[音乐]
covered head to toe in Nike. But this
从头到脚都穿着耐克装备。 但这
isn't a picture of Nike's maintained
并非耐克保持
dominance, rather it's what the company
统治地位的写照，而是该公司
hopes will be the beginning of a
希望开启
comeback story.
复兴之路的开端。
These American athletes are wearing a
这些美国运动员穿着
Nike sub-label called All Conditions
耐克旗下名为 All Conditions
Gear, or ACG. And the fact that this
Gear（简称 ACG）的子品牌服装。 而这一事实
hasn't reached name brand recognition
并未使该品牌
across a public audience highlights one
在公众中获得知名度，这凸显了
of the brand's many fumbles in the past
该品牌在过去
20 years.
20 年中犯下的众多错误之一。
unique path in the last decade. Running
过去十年，跑鞋市场走了一条独特的道路。
shoes of all sorts are as popular as
各种跑鞋依然很受欢迎
ever, but trail running shoes, a
，但越野跑鞋，这种
comparatively rugged off-road option,
相对坚固耐用的越野跑鞋，
are especially [music] hot.
尤其火爆。
While trail runners make up a fraction
虽然越野跑鞋在
of total running shoe sales, a number
跑鞋总销量中
cited at 12% in 2022, they're steadily
所占比例很小（2022 年仅为 12%），但其预计年复合增长率正稳步
outpacing conventional running shoes in
超过传统跑鞋
projected annual compound growth.
。
Running shoes are in, but trail runners
跑鞋很流行，但越野跑鞋
are even more in. And just as trainers,
更受欢迎。就像运动鞋、
basketball shoes, and running shoes
篮球鞋和跑鞋
found their way into casual fashion in
过去逐渐成为休闲时尚的一部分一样
the past, now so too have trail runners.
，现在越野跑鞋也加入了这一行列。
cushioned trail shoes like Hoka have
像 Hoka 这样专注于生产最大限度缓冲越野鞋的品牌，已经逐渐成为人们
wormed their way into everyday shoe
日常鞋履选择的一部分，
rotations for service jobs and weekend
无论是服务行业的工作还是周末的
chores alike. Salomon's rugged mountain
家务，都离不开它们。  Salomon 坚固耐用的山地
running shoes have unexpectedly become
跑鞋出人意料地
popular with Gen Z'ers in the urban
在
environs of New York City. It goes
纽约市的 Z 世代年轻人中流行起来。 它还不止于此
further, too. This outdoor gear
。 户外装备的
popularity has expanded beyond shoes.
流行已经扩展到鞋类以外的领域。
It's called Gorpcore. It's led to urban
它叫做Gorpcore。 这导致都市
fashion and urban celebrities turning to
时尚和都市名人开始青睐
outdoor brands and their Gore-Tex
户外品牌及其 Gore-Tex
offerings to establish today's taste. It
产品，从而确立了当今的时尚品味。 这
means a big uptick in sales for trail
意味着越野
running suppliers, of which Nike is
跑装备供应商的销量将大幅增长，耐克正
desperately trying to catch up by
竭力追赶，计划
relaunching its outdoor line in 2026.
在 2026 年重新推出其户外产品线。
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
&gt;&gt; What's glaring is not only that Nike is
显而易见的是，耐克不仅
late to the trend, but the fact that
错过了这股潮流，而且
this is a trend they helped establish
这股潮流正是他们帮助建立的
[music] but lacked the vision to see
[音乐]，但他们却缺乏远见卓识，未能将其贯彻
through. Nike launched its first trail
到底。 耐克于 1984 年推出了第一款越野
shoe in 1984. It launched ACG in 1988,
跑鞋。1988 年，它推出了 ACG 系列，
and it helped invent the trail shoe,
并帮助发明了越野跑鞋，
taking the tread of hiking boots and
将登山靴的鞋底与
matching them with the uppers of running
跑鞋的鞋面相结合
shoes. It was a visionary in the
。 它在技术上具有远见卓识
technology, and it began to build out
，并且也开始构建
the style, too, blending performance
风格，将性能
with the signature Nike brashness, the
与耐克标志性的张扬、
color, the prints, the fun that the
色彩、印花以及
outdoor space lacked. But in the 2000s,
户外空间所缺乏的乐趣融合在一起。 但在 2000 年代，
they let the branch wither on the vine.
他们却任由这根枝条枯萎凋零。
The lack of follow-through and vision
缺乏执行力和远见
became a theme.
成为一个普遍存在的问题。
This is Nike's total market share of
这是耐克
athletic shoes in 2000. It holds a
在2000年运动鞋市场的总份额。它
dominant 42% of all sales and outpaces
占据了42%的销售份额，超过了
its next three largest competitors
其排名第二和第三的三大竞争对手的
combined. And this is what its market
总和。 这是它
share looked like in 2022. With the
在 2022 年的市场份额情况。随着
Jordan brand under the Nike umbrella, it
Jordan 品牌归入耐克旗下，它
still maintains a similarly strong 36%
仍然保持着同样强劲的 36% 的
market share. It still outpaces the next
市场份额。 虽然它仍然超过了该领域排名第二至第三的
three largest brands in the space
三大品牌的总和
combined, but market share serves as
，但市场份额
only a freeze-frame in time. It doesn't
只能反映当时的状况。 它没有
consider momentum, and these brands that
考虑发展势头，而这些
are beginning to claw at market share
开始争夺市场份额的品牌
are making big moves. Hoka, New Balance,
正在采取重大举措。  Hoka、New Balance、
Saucony, Puma, and ASICS are some of the
Saucony、Puma 和 ASICS 等
names, along with Brooks and On, that
品牌，以及 Brooks 和 On 等品牌，都
are leading the charge in the specialty
在专业跑步鞋市场中处于领先地位
running market. Now, specialty running
。 如今，“专业
shoes is a rather vague term, but
跑鞋”一词含义相当模糊，但
effectively it's a host of brands that
实际上指的是许多
are innovating hard in specific niches.
在特定细分市场努力创新的品牌。
More broadly, it can be understood as
更广义地说，可以理解为在
companies that are out-innovating Nike.
创新方面超越耐克的公司。
In specialty running shops, stores with
在专业的跑步用品商店里，有受过
educated staff selling running shoes to
专业训练的店员向
runners, essentially the simplest way to
跑步者销售跑鞋，这是
understand runners' preferences, Brooks
了解跑步者偏好的最简单方法。Brooks
and Hoka lead the way and account for
和 Hoka 引领潮流，占据了
almost half of sales. New Balance, On,
近一半的销售额。  New Balance、On
and Saucony make up the next 29%, while
和 Saucony 占据了接下来的 29%，而
Nike, which has pivoted away from
Nike 已经放弃了
in-store sales and deemphasized running
店内销售，并且全面降低了跑步产品的占比
across the board, sat at less [music]
，其占比不到
than 5%.
5%。
In speed, a category Nike running once
在速度方面，耐克跑步鞋曾
dominated with its Vaporfly line that
凭借其 Vaporfly 系列占据主导地位，该系列一度
became the world's fastest road running
成为世界上速度最快的公路
shoe, Nike has been caught by Adidas and
跑鞋，但如今耐克已被阿迪达斯追赶，
in the lab passed by Puma. In comfort
在研发方面也被彪马超越。 在舒适性
and cushioning, concepts foreign to
和缓冲性方面，
running shoes prior to Nike, it's been
耐克之前的跑鞋从未考虑过这些概念，但如今它已被
overtaken by the maximally supportive
支撑性极佳的
Hokas and corrective Brooks shoes, both
Hoka 和矫正型跑鞋所超越，这两款跑鞋不仅
popular in running but also brand
在跑步领域广受欢迎，而且也是医院工作等需要
leaders for on-your-feet type jobs like
长时间站立的工作的领先品牌
hospital work. Even in unapologetically
。 即使在
bold design, Nike's been passed by On
大胆前卫的设计方面，耐克也已经超越了 On
Running.
Running。
On's come-up feels reminiscent to that
On 是一款瑞士鞋履，以其 CloudTec 技术而闻名，既引人注目又舒适无比。On 的发展历程让人想起
of Nike's. Rather than using a waffle
耐克。
On's founder, Oliver Bernhard, a
On 的创始人 Oliver Bernhard 是一名
triathlete, couldn't find a shoe that
铁人三项运动员，他找不到一双
would properly address some lingering
能够真正解决他长期
Achilles pain, so he set out to create
跟腱疼痛问题的鞋子，于是他决定自己创造一些
something new. In 2010, the concept of
新的东西，而不是用华夫饼机来制作独一无二的鞋底。  2010 年，
CloudTec was born when Bernhard attached
当 Bernhard 将
bisected bit of garden hose to the heel
一截花园软管连接到
of his shoe. Before deciding to build a
鞋跟上时，CloudTec 的概念就此诞生。 在决定
brand around the idea, he took it to his
围绕这个理念打造品牌之前，他曾向
sponsor, who ultimately turned the idea
赞助商提出过这个想法，但最终被赞助商
down. The sponsor was Nike. Nike missed
拒绝了。 赞助商是耐克。 耐克错失了
on On and fell behind across the board
On 音乐，并
in running because [music] it had spent
在跑步领域全面落后，因为过去十年它一直在疲于应对音乐领域的各种
fires.
危机。
In 2004, Nike did something it hadn't
2004年，耐克做了一件它
done before. It brought in a CEO from
以前从未做过的事情。 它从公司外部聘请了一位首席执行官
outside the company, and it paid for
，并为此付出了
that decision. While William Perez only
代价。 威廉·佩雷斯担任
lasted 2 years as CEO, it set Nike back.
首席执行官仅两年，但这却给耐克造成了损失。
company, Perez focused his efforts on
佩雷斯摒弃了公司以往依靠直觉展望未来的做法，转而采用数据驱动的方式，将精力集中在
sales in the present, rather than
当下的销售上，而不是具有
era-defining innovation. Replaced by
时代意义的创新上。 在
Nike lifer Mark Parker, Nike would
耐克老将马克·帕克接任后，耐克
regain its bearings, but it had to
重回正轨，但它也不得不
navigate some scandal, too.
应对一些丑闻。
2009, then Lance Armstrong's doping in
2009 年泰格·伍兹的婚姻问题曝光，2013 年兰斯·阿姆斯特朗的兴奋剂丑闻
2013, put the giant in PR [music]
，让这家巨头陷入了公关
defense mode, a position difficult to
防御模式，这种局面很难进行
innovate from. And even in the spaces
创新。 即使在
they continued to push innovation,
他们不断推动创新的领域，
distance running in particular, scandal
特别是长跑领域，丑闻也
rocked the company. The immensely
震动了这家公司。 马拉松运动员兼教练阿尔贝托·萨拉萨尔是一位非常
successful marathoner, then marathon
成功的马拉松运动员，他
coach Alberto Salazar, was so central to
对
the Nike distance running project that
耐克长跑项目至关重要，以至于
he had a building named after him. But
有一栋建筑以他的名字命名。 但
that changed first with allegations of
情况先是发生了变化，先是
his athletes doping, then an
他的运动员被指控服用兴奋剂，然后是
investigation into the issue that saw
针对此事的调查导致
Salazar banned, and finally athlete
萨拉扎尔被禁赛，最后是运动员
allegations over abusive conduct from
指控
the disgraced coach from 2015 to 2019.
这位声名狼藉的教练在2015年至2019年期间存在虐待行为。
At the same time, the company faced a
与此同时，该公司还面临一起
sexual discrimination lawsuit alleging
性别歧视诉讼，指控
that the boys' club culture of the
该公司内部的男性俱乐部文化
company had resulted in discrimination,
导致了性别歧视、
retaliation, and unfair wages [music]
报复和不公平的薪酬
across sexes. The two scandals
。 这两起丑闻
ultimately culminated with Parker
最终导致帕克
stepping down [music] as CEO.
辞去了音乐公司首席执行官的职务。
Weighed down by an increasingly
由于
tarnished reputation, Nike began looking
声誉日益受损，耐克开始回顾
backwards instead of forward, and again
过去而不是展望未来，并再次
brought in leadership from outside the
从公司外部引入领导层
company. This time it was John Donahoe
。 这次掌舵的是约翰·多纳霍
at the helm, and with a mandate to build
，他的任务是
out the company's digital footprint, he
拓展公司的数字版图，他
played the hits, and [music] at first it
播放热门歌曲，而且一开始效果不错
worked. Nike went direct-to-consumer
。 新冠疫情爆发后，耐克立即采取了直接面向消费者的销售模式；与此同时，
right as COVID hit, and right as a
一部
much-anticipated Michael Jordan
备受期待的迈克尔·乔丹
documentary debuted during the pandemic,
纪录片也在疫情期间上映，耐克大力
they pushed the Jordans and Air Force
推广了乔丹鞋和空军
lines. Sales boomed for the moment, but
一号系列产品。 销售额一度飙升，但
innovation flatlined, relationships with
创新停滞不前，与
shoe carriers and wholesalers soured,
鞋类零售商和批发商的关系恶化，就在
in-person shopping roared back to life.
实体店购物重新焕发活力之际，耐克却让出了货架空间。
It since navigated the company's worst
此后，该公司经历了 2024 年最糟糕的
day in 2024 as stocks dropped 20% in a
一天，股票一天下跌了 20%
single day, then reported its worst fall
，然后在 2025 年公布了最糟糕的秋季
revenue in 2025 with an 11.5% [music]
收入，音乐收入
year-over-year drop. Nike had bottomed
同比下降了 11.5%。 耐克跌入
out because in a business of
谷底，是因为在这个以
storytelling, it had lost its own plot.
讲故事为核心的商业领域，它迷失了方向。
It was no longer making shoes for the
它不再为未来制造鞋子
future, it was relying on those from the
，而是依赖于
past. It was no longer producing an
过去的鞋子。 它不再能生产出
image or a product that people could
人们可以信赖的形象或产品
trust. It was no longer the scrappy
。 它不再是那个顽强拼搏的
winner, it was the bloated institution
胜利者，而是那个臃肿不堪、
so scared of failing. Never in its
害怕失败的机构。 耐克的音乐品牌在其历史上从未像
something of the past until the present,
现在这样给人一种过时的感觉，
as athlete after athlete has turned away
因为越来越多的运动员开始放弃与
[music] from the brand.
该品牌的音乐合作。
But now Donahoe is gone, and in his
但现在多纳霍已经不在了，
place is Elliott Hill, and he knows the
取而代之的是埃利奥特·希尔，他对
company's story as well as anyone.
公司的历史了如指掌。
there's company-wide hope that Hill can
希尔于 1988 年以实习生的身份加入耐克，公司上下都希望他能让
get Nike back to what it was best at.
耐克重回巅峰。
And so far, there's reason for some
目前来看，还是有一些理由保持
guarded optimism. The relaunch of ACG
谨慎乐观的。  ACG 的重新推出
has been a shot in the arm, while Hill
犹如一剂强心针，而希尔也
has pushed hard to get Nike back into
一直努力推动耐克重返
the wholesale game and back on shelves.
批发市场，重新上架销售。
Relationships are on the mend, too, as
各方关系也在逐渐修复，
the new CEO has taken off on business
新任首席执行官已奔波于一次又一次的商务
trip after business trip to mend
旅行，以修复
relationships between some of the
一些
sport's biggest names and biggest brands
体育界最知名人士和最大品牌之间的关系，
to [music] ensure they stay with the
确保他们继续与耐克保持合作关系
swoosh. Time will tell if these
。 时间会证明这些
relationships can hold and if Hill can
关系能否维持下去，以及希尔能否
build back consumer trust that's waned
重建
over the past 10 [music] years. But at
过去 10 年音乐界逐渐衰落的消费者信任。 但从
its core, the company might be back as
本质上讲，这家公司可能已经重振旗鼓，因为
it's finally finding its fight again.
它终于重新找到了奋斗的目标。
When we're putting these videos
在制作这些视频时
together, what can also prove to be a
，
fight is finding the right clips and
找到合适的片段和
footage that helps tell the story we're
素材来讲述我们
trying to tell. That's where the sponsor
想要讲述的故事，也可能是一场艰苦的战斗。 这就引出了我们
of today's video comes in, Storyblocks.
今天视频的赞助商 Storyblocks。
Since the beginning of this channel and
从本频道创立之初到
through to today, Storyblocks as a
今天，Storyblocks
service has been instrumental in making
服务在这一切的实现过程中发挥了至关重要的作用
all this happen. Going out into the
。 到
world to film is wildly expensive
世界各地拍摄音乐非常昂贵
[music] and time-consuming, while
且耗时，而获得视频
licensing footage, whether as a one-off
素材的授权，无论是单次
deal or through a different service, is
交易还是通过其他服务，
quite costly, too, as you're often
成本也相当高，因为你通常是
paying by the clip. Storyblocks, in this
按片段付费的。 从这个意义上讲
way, is different. It's a subscription
，Storyblocks 就有所不同。 这是一项订阅
service, so you pay a flat rate for
服务，所以你只需支付固定费用即可观看
everything they have and not go by the
他们提供的所有内容，而不是按
clip. And that's massive because
片段付费。 这意义重大，因为
Storyblocks has a ton of helpful
Storyblocks 提供了大量有用的
services. For one, there's the catalog
服务。 首先，这里有
of footage. It's all human-made, it's
影像资料库。 它完全由人类打造，
easy to navigate, and it has something
易于操作，几乎可以满足
to just about cover every ask, whether
所有需求，无论
you're trying [music] to tell your story
您是想
with compelling visuals as a content
作为内容
creator or a business owner. Storyblocks
创作者还是企业主，通过音乐和引人入胜的视觉效果来讲述您的故事。  Storyblocks
is more than just a catalog of clips,
不仅仅是一个视频片段库
too. They have music, they have sound
。 它们包含音乐、
effects, and editing templates that are
音效和编辑模板，可以
going to speed up your workflow and
加快您的工作流程，并使
professionalize your product. Long
您的产品更加专业。 早
before the company sponsored videos like
在公司赞助此类视频之前
this, we used the service, so I can tell
，我们就使用过这项服务，所以我可以
you from personal experience that
根据个人经验告诉你，
Storyblocks is going to save you time,
Storyblocks 可以节省你的时间，
it's going to give you some peace of
让你
mind because all it has to offer is
安心，因为它提供的所有内容都是获得
licensed and ready to go, and finally
授权且即刻可用，最后，
[music] it's going to save you some
[音乐]它
money right now because they're offering
现在还能帮你省钱，因为他们正在提供
15% off the annual plan. Storyblocks has
年度计划 15% 的折扣。  Storyblocks
been a huge aid to this channel, and it
对本频道帮助很大，
could be a huge aid to your visual
对你的视觉叙事也可能有很大的帮助
storytelling, too. So, start telling
。 所以，现在就前往 storyblocks.com/wendover，开始讲述
better stories by heading to
更精彩的故事吧！
plans by following our link only for a
通过我们的链接，即可在
limited time.
限时内享受年度套餐 15% 的折扣。